Pressing the 'magazine release' frees
the magazine from the lower receiver.
Rounds are loaded, and held under
high force of the magazine spring.
It's then inserted into the magwell
and secured by the 'magazine catch'.
Pulling and releasing the 'charginghandle'
chambers the first round.
The charging handle forces the
'bolt carrier group' to the rear.
As it comes back,
the 'actionspring' is compressed.
As the carrier returns forward,
the 'bolt' strips the top cartridge from
the magazine and guides it into the chamber.
Housed within the bolt carrier, is the bolt.
The bolt contains several 'locking lugs'
that engage with the barrel extension lugs.
As it makes contact with the barrel breechface,
the bolt turns and locks into place.
The locking function is due to the
'cam pin' housed within the bolt.
The pin rides along a 'track' in the
bolt carrier, allowing it to rotate.
When the bolt is open, it's
locked in the forward position
and can only rotate once the cam pin has
cleared the 'recess' in the upper receiver.
In the rare occurrence where the bolt fails to
fully close, the 'forward assist' may be used.
Pressing the forward assist plunger
allows the pawl to engage with the
notches cut into the bolt carrier.
This will force the carrier forward
until the bolt is fully locked.
With the selector taken off the safe
position, the AR-15 is ready to fire.
A 'recess' cut into the selector
permits trigger movement.
As the trigger is pulled, the
'hammer' is released from the sear.
The hammer spring drives the hammer
forward to strike the 'firing pin',
causing it to travel forward
and impact the cartridge primer.
Within the primer
is the 'ignitioncompound' and an 'anvil'.
As the firing pin strikes the
primer, a spark is created,
igniting the propellant inside the cartridge.
The expanding gases propel
the bullet down the barrel,
where 'rifling grooves' impart
stabilizing spin on the bullet.
The gases escape through a small port
in the barrel.
Through the gas tube...
and into the 'bolt carrier
key', forcing it to the rear.
The 'extractor' grips the rim of the spent
cartridge case, and holds it against the bolt face
until the 'ejector' forces it through the ejection
port, striking the 'deflector' as it exits.
As the bolt carrier comes back, it
returns the hammer to its cocked position,
and stays held back by the 'disconnector'.
When the 'buffer' reaches the
back of the receiver extension,
the 'action spring' returns
the bolt carrier forward.
As it returns, the bolt strips a new cartridge
from the magazine and directs it into the chamber.
Simultaneously, the extractor clips
into the rim of the new cartridge.
Releasing the trigger releases
the hammer from the disconnector,
and again the 'trigger sear' assumes control of
the hammer, readying the rifle for another shot.
Military variants of the
AR-15, such as the M16 and M4,
add a third option for fully automatic fire.
The inclusion of an 'auto sear', and
a hook on the back of the hammer,
allow continuous operation
while the trigger is depressed.
Moving the selector to AUTO, the
disconnector is disabled from moving,
and will be unable to hold the hammer when fired.
The auto sear is now able to rotate
into a recess in the selector.
After a shot is taken, the auto sear rotates
forward as the bolt carrier comes back,
taking control of the hammer.
As the bolt carrier returns forward, the
back of the carrier trips the auto sear,
releasing the hammer just after the bolt closes.
Releasing the trigger, allows the sear
to again assume control of the hammer.
In order to conserve ammunition
and promote greater accuracy,
a burst mode was later introduced.
With the auto sear still present,
the disconnector is split in two.
The left disconnector takes control
of the hammer in semi-fire mode.
Switching to BURST fire,
disables the left disconnector.
The 'burst cam' and 'clutch spring' allow
the M4 to fire up to three rounds at a time.
The clutch spring expands to rotate the
cam only when the hammer moves in reverse.
As the trigger rotates forward, the burst
disconnector engages the deep notch of the cam.
The cam rotates as the hammer is brought back, and
the disconnector engages the first small notch.
This isn't enough for the disconnector to hold thehammer,
and the auto sear is
tripped to fire another round.
The cam rotates again and the cycle is repeated.
The cam rotates once more, and the
hook engages the third, deeper notch.
The disconnector is now able to
reach the hammer, holding it back.
The trigger must be released and pulled
again to fire another three rounds.
Once the final round of ammunition has been fired,
the 'magazine follower' pushes up on the 'boltcatch',
holding it open as it returns forward.
Inserting a new magazine and pressing
the bolt catch, will chamber a new round.
Using a cartridge, the front sight post
can be adjusted up or down for zeroing.
The rear sight includes two 'apertures'.
For short ranges, the zero
to two-hundred meter is used.
For longer ranges, the smaller aperture is used.
Turning the 'elevation knob' will raise and
lower the sight depending on the distance.
The knob on the right of the sight
is used to adjust for 'windage'.
The calibration lines on the back of the sight
help control windage adjustments during firing.
The carry handle on the AR-15 can be removed
to allow for alternative optics,
such as holographic sights.
Or longer range scopes, like the ACOG.
Many ARs are equipped with an adjustable stock.
The stock rides along the 'receiver extension',
commonly referred to as the buffer tube.
Pressing the release lever,
moving it to the desired position and
releasing it, will lock it in place.
The 'ejection port cover' can be
closed when the rifle is not in use,
to protect the inner parts from outside elements.
The cover opens automatically
when the rifle is fired.